This stuff is דף סז Daf Samech Zayin 67 and we pick
up at the גמרא Gemara right after the משנה. Mishnah. And the
משנה Mishnah was a nice extended debate between רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
and רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua where the question was if you do
one of these קרבנות, korbanot, these bird קרבנות korbanot correctly, then the
one that doesn't have מעילה me'ilah is the חטאת chatat because the
חטאת chatat after it's שחט shechted and done correctly or מליקה'd melikah
and done correctly can be eaten by the כהנים. kohanim. But if
you do them incorr- but the עולה olah still has מעילה me'ilah
because nobody gets to eat it. If you do them incorrectly and
nobody gets to eat even the חטאת, chatas, you know, and certainly
the עולה olah you de-rally even more then they both have מעילה
me'ilah because it can't be bene- nobody can benefit from them. But
comes along רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua with a very strange idea. And
רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua says if you do the עולה olah like
a חטאת, chatat, you do it at the bottom of the altar,
you do it with the intent of a חטאת, chatat, you do
the מליקה melikah like a חטאת chatat only one of the סימנים
simanim not two of the סימנים, simanim, that somehow takes it out
of the category of an עולה, olah, puts it in the category
of a חטאת, chatat, you somehow redefined it and now there is
no מעילה. me'ilah. Now you can say there's an interesting question, is
he really saying it's a חטאת? chatas? Do the כהנים kohanim get
to eat it? Right?
We'll discuss that in the גמרא. Gemara. The short answer is no.
It's just enough out- like a חטאת chatas that you don't get
מעילה me'ilah but it's not really a חטאת. chatas. But it's one
of the other. Anyway, certainly somehow there's a redefinition of this like
a חטאת chatas and רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer doesn't know where the
heck רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua is getting this. It doesn't work by
any other sacrifice that you get to redefine it, right? How do
you, I mean, you know, how does this work by the עולה?
olah? And that was the debate in the משנה. Mishnah. We're going
to continue with it in the גמרא. Gemara. So let's take a
look at the גמרא. Gemara. Yes.
What did he initiate it as an עולה? olah?
When you sanctified it. You said this bird should be as an
עולה olah as an עולה. olah.
Oh so he had the intent.
Yeah, no, not just the intent, that's the sanctification. When you sanctified
it a week ago, whatever, before you brought it to the בית
המקדש Beis Hamikdash you sanctified it as an עולה olah and now
when the כהן kohen is bringing it he's treating it and thinking
of it as a חטאת. chatas.
So isn't that really the wrong intent then through out?
Right, which is what רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says. He says you
should just be more invalidating it and more taking it out of
reach, making it more מעילה. me'ilah. How does taking something that is
an עולה, olah, you know, and pretending that it's a חטאת chatat
and treating it like a חטאת chatat make it into a חטאת?
chatat? Okay that's basically right. That's why רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua is
such a strange idea. So
let's
take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. תניא, Tanya, we taught in
a ברייתא. brayta. אמר ליה Amar leh רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer ליה
leh רבי יהושע. Rabbi Yehoshua. So רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer said to
challenge
רבי יהושע. Rabbi Yehoshua. הביא ואחר Avi'eh ve'achar like a big, one
of the big animals, none of this- this doesn't work. אשם ששחטו
בצפון לשם שלמים. Asham she-shechato batzafon leshem shelamim. Let's say you, and
this we're starting by this to build up to cases that are
more and more similar to רבי יהושע's Rabbi Yehoshua case. So the
first case there's going to be a number of points that's not
exactly similar and then we're going to slowly build up. Okay, so
here's the first example. You slaughtered an אשם asham in the right
place, in the north, but you did it in the intent of
a שלמים. shelamim. יוכיח שינוי שמו ומועלין בו. Yochi'ach shinuy shemo u-mo'alin
bo. You switched the name and
nevertheless there is מעילה. me'ilah. Okay, now it's a little funny because
רש"י Rashi says there's not exactly מעילה me'ilah because by an אשם
asham it's kosher and once you put the זריקת הדם zerikah hadam
there actually isn't מעילה. me'ilah. But there's מעילה me'ilah before זריקת הדם.
zerikah hadam. So it's like a lot of points of not good
comparison. You know, there there's only מעילה me'ilah for a temporary period
of time. There is מעילה me'ilah by the שלמים shelamim itself, so
it's not exactly clear what's so compelling about that example that should
be a counterproof to his case of the of the עולה olah
and the חטאת. chatas. Because the עולה olah okay but anyway but
let's see where this goes. We'll get closer to the example. ואף
אתה תמה על עולה שאף על פי ששינה שמה שימעלו בה. Ve'af
attah tamah al olah she'af al pi she-shinah shemah she-yim'alu bah. So
so what if you did a שינוי שם? shinuy shem? You did
a שינוי שם shinuy shem and there's still מעילה. me'ilah. By if
you switch the עולה olah to a bird חטאת. chatat. אמר לו
Amar lo רבי יהושע. Rabbi Yehoshua. רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua said back
לא, lo, no, it's not a good comparison. אם אמרת באשם ששינה
שמו לא שינה מקומו. Im amarta be'asham she-shinah shemo lo shinah mekomo.
You didn't really make the אשם asham like a שלמים. shelamim. You
still did it in the north. So the- I am really making
my bird עולה olah like a חטאת, chatat, I did it in
the place of חטאת. chatat. תאמר בעולה ששינה שמה ושינה מקומה? Tomar
be'olah she-shinah shemah ve-shinah mekomah? My example, I've really made it like
a חטאת, chatat, I did it in the place of חטאת. chatat.
אמר לו Amar lo רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
said okay fine, let's try this case. אשם ששחטו בדרום. Asham she-shechato
badarom. Let's say you slaughtered it in the place of the שלמים,
shelamim, the south, which is not an acceptable place for an אשם.
asham. לשם שלמים Leshem shelamim and you did it for the sake
of a שלמים. shelamim. יוכיח ששינה שמו ושינה מקומו ומועלין בו. Yochi'ach
she-shinah shemo ve-shinah mekomo u-mo'alin bo. You changed both factors and there's
still מעילה. me'ilah. Okay so אף אתה תמה על עולה שאף על
פי ששינה שמה ושינה מקומה מועלין בה. Af attah tamah al olah
she'af al pi she-shinah shemah ve-shinah mekomah mo'alin bah. So by an
עולה olah too, a bird עולה, olah, just because you made it
like a חטאת chatat there should still be מעילה. me'ilah. אמר
ליה Amar lei רבי יהושע. Rabbi Yehoshua. רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua back
to him, לא, lo, that's not a good example. אם אמרת באשם
ששינה שמו ושינה מקומו, Im amarta be'asham she-shinah shemo ve-shinah mekomo, okay
there you did two things to make it like a שלמים, shelamim,
you called it a שלמים, shelamim, you know, you acted pretended like
it was a שלמים shelamim and you did it in the place
of the שלמים. shelamim. But nevertheless ולא שינה מעשיו. ve-lo shinah ma'asav.
There was nothing you did differently about how you actually did it.
You slaughtered it like you would slaughter an אשם. asham. You
sprinkled... That you
can't compare that to the עולה olah that you made like a
חטאת, chatat, 'cause there not only did you call it a חטאת
chatat and do it in the place of a חטאת, chatat, you
actually did the act of a חטאת. chatat. Now what's the act
of a חטאת? chatat? So we already said in the משנה mishnah
but the גמרא gemara doesn't realize this yet, okay, we already said
that the act of a חטאת chatat is you shechted only, you
did מליקה melikah on only one סימן siman and not on two
סימנים, simanim, okay. Thank you so much. So therefore, thank you, so
therefore
he says what do you call it? It's you haven't completely done
it like a חטאת. chatat. And since you haven't completely done it
like like the other thing, by the עולה olah you've done completely
like a חטאת, chatat, so there you can change its categorization. But
in your counterexample, you haven't completely done the אשם asham like a
שלמים. shlamim.
So אמר רבא, amar Rava, so רבא Rava
said is there a distinction between שלמים shlamim and אשם asham in
terms of מעילה? me'ilah?
Well, that's the funny thing. That's why it's such a bizarre example.
Because by both a שלמים shlamim and an אשם, asham, you know,
until you sprinkle the blood there's מעילה, me'ilah, even if done normally.
After you sprinkle the blood, you know, there isn't מעילה me'ilah on
the meat. So it's like such a bizarre counterexample, right? Because here
which is sort of you know what we sort of already primed
for that from from the משנה mishnah where where רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer says no, by a חטאת, chatat, you know, חטאת chatat there's
no מעילה me'ilah at all. And that's why this takes it out.
Now presumably he would say the bird goes out of מעילה me'ilah
only after you do the זריקת הדם. zrikat hadam. But as an
עולה olah you did the זריקת הדם, zrikat hadam, it would have
had מעילה. me'ilah. Because you've treated it like a חטאת chatat and
you did the זריקת הדם, zrikat hadam, there's no מעילה. me'ilah. So
that like you understand what he's saying? This counterexample doesn't make sense,
right? Because in this counterexample you haven't been זורק הדם zorek hadam
yet. So of course there's still going to be מעילה, me'ilah, right?
And after you're זורק הדם, zorek hadam, there isn't מעילה me'ilah either
way. So it's a very strange—it's not clear like why he lets
him get away with this counterexample,
because it's not really compared well to his case. His case he's
talking about after you did זריקה, zrikah, and the reason there's no
מעילה me'ilah is because the thing you shifted it to was a
thing that did not have, you know, that did not have מעילה,
me'ilah, right? Which is sort of the example in the משנה mishnah
was a closer counterexample, okay, but because in the example in the
משנה mishnah it's an עולה olah and a שלמים, shlamim, right? So
then you could say if it were fully an עולה olah even
after זריקה zrikah there would be מעילה. me'ilah. I want to argue
to you that if you were to treat it like a שלמים
shlamim based on your logic, after זריקה zrikah there should not be
מעילה. me'ilah. That would have been a good counterexample, and in the
משנה mishnah his response was, but by even a שלמים shlamim there's
elements of מעילה me'ilah by the אימורים, imurim, so that doesn't totally
switch its category. Okay, but the אשם asham example and the אשם
שלמים asham shlamim is like not a good counterexample. Okay,
but we're just going to go with it. Okay. So the גמרא
gemara says like this. ונימא. v'neima. So anyway his response at this
stage is not that you haven't done זריקת הדם zrikat hadam yet,
right, which is what was just being pointed out. His response at
this stage was you haven't made it totally like the other thing.
By the bird עולה olah and the חטאת chatat you made it
totally like the חטאת chatat because not only was it the place
and the intent, it was how you did it. Here the act
itself, the שחיטה, shchitah, the זריקה, zrikah, whatever, was exactly the same.
So you haven't totally made it like the other thing. So אמר
רבא, amar Rava, so רבא Rava said ונימא ליה אשם שחטו בדרום
לשם שלמים בשינוי בעלים. v'neima leh asham sheshachato badarom l'shem shlamim b'shinui
be'alim. Why didn't he sort of add another thing to make it
you know in his אשם asham and שלמים shlamim case? You did
it in the south for the sake of a שלמים shlamim and
you had intention of a different owner, okay. ששינה שמו ושינה מקומו
ושינה מעשיה. sheshina shemo v'shina mekomo v'shina ma'aseha. You did you did
yet a third thing that was different. Now that is again a
bizarre question because that means they're not really understanding, you know,
what רבי אליעזר's Rabbi Eliezer's point is. Intending for a different owner
is not making it more like a שלמים, shlamim, right? I have,
I, you know, I go ahead and I, you know, I take,
you know, David's אשם, asham, I do it in the south, not
in the north. I say it's a שלמים, shlamim, so those are
two things that I made it like a שלמים. shlamim. And then
the גמרא gemara says, oh, and then also just say you're doing
it for the sake of Seth and not for the sake of
David. It's like okay, so you did something different. But the point
wasn't different, the point was are you doing enough things to make
it like the new thing? Doing it for the sake of a
different owner isn't making it like the new category we're trying to
pretend it's in. So that's what the גמרא gemara sort of said.
The גמרא gemara sort of now sort of says at this stage,
since רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer didn't answer that, he realized that for
רבי יהושע's Rabbi Yehoshua's point was not just you're changing things, oh
you're doing things different somehow that's magic and takes it out of
מעילה. me'ilah. He realized that רבי אליעזר's Rabbi Eliezer's point was specifically
that you're recategorizing it and that's why he didn't have a good
counterexample to—רבי יהושע's Rabbi Yehoshua's point was that. And that's why he
did not have a good counterexample to רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua because
there is nothing else that you could make like the, like the
עולה olah and the חטאת chatat of the bird that you could
fully recategorize to the way you can by the bird חטאת chatat
and the עולה. olah. Okay, so he says like this. So אמר
רבא. amar Rava. So why didn't he say that? ושינה מעשיה. v'shina
ma'aseha. מדלא קאמר ליה הכי שמע מינה נחית רבי אליעזר לטעמיה. mid'lo
ka'amar leh hachi shma mina nachit Rabbi Eliezer l'ta'ameh. Rabbi Yehoshua.
Now when you normally say he's נחית nachis לטעמיה, l'taimei, he goes
down to his reason, it means that he actually, like he followed
his reasons, like he ruled like his reasons. But here it's sort
of saying like, like the light bulb went off in Rabbi Eliezer's
head. You know? Rabbi Yehoshua said this completely bizarre thing. Oh, if
you change an עולה olah enough, if you do enough weird things
with an עולה, olah, there's no מעילה. me'ilah. And Rabbi Eliezer's like,
what are you talking about? Like you could do weird things with
other קרבנות korbanot and there's still מעילה. me'ilah. And then he's saying,
oh, that's what you mean. Like he gave enough pushback that he
started realizing that what you're really telling me, Rabbi Yehoshua, is that's
because the things you did somehow recategorized it. Because you did all
these three חטאת chatas things with this עולה, olah, to some degree
you made it a חטאת. chatas. I don't have a counterexample, because
any of the large mammals, by the way, the act of שחיטה
shechitah is always going to be the same. You could change where
you're doing it, you could change your thought, but the act of
שחיטה shechitah is always going to be the same. So I really
don't have a good counterexample where you completely recategorize something and the
old category was a מעילה me'ilah one and the new one is
not. So I still disagree with you, but I can't disprove you
because I don't have a good counterexample. Okay, so נחית nachis Rabbi
Eliezer לטעמיה l'taimei d'Rabbi Yehoshua. He finally, you know, got the idea
what Rabbi Yehoshua saying. דאמר רב אדא בר אהבה, d'amar Rav Adda
bar Ahava, and now we're going to explain Rabbi Yehoshua in a
way that's even sharper than we've explained it until now, because until
now we just said if you do enough things like a חטאת,
chatas, somehow you magically turn it into a חטאת. chatas. Okay, but
now we're going to be a little bit more precise why that
דווקא davka works. It's because it's not just that there are enough
things, it's actually about a moment in time. So let's take a
look at what he's going to say and how a moment in
time is critical. Okay, דאמר רב אדא בר אהבה, d'amar Rav Adda
bar Ahava, אמר האי רבי יהושע, amar hai Rabbi Yehoshua, Rabbi Yehoshua
used to say, this is the explanation of Rabbi Yehoshua. עולת העוף,
olat ha'of, this bird עולה, olah, שעשה למטה כמעשה חטאת, she'asahu lematah
k'ma'aseh chatas, you did it below like a חטאת, chatas, לשם חטאת,
leshem chatas, for the sake of a חטאת. chatas. It's in the
place of a חטאת, chatas, it's for the sake of a חטאת.
chatas. כיון שמלק בסימן אחד, keivan shemalak b'siman echad, here we can
go to my nice beautiful picture here of the bird. You did
one סימן, siman, okay, and that now is מעשה חטאת. ma'aseh chatas.
Okay, you now did what would have made it a valid חטאת.
chatas. So now the focus here right now is a moment in
time. At this moment, you cut through the trachea, you did not
cut through the esophagus, okay. You have, from the perspective, if we
were to look at this through the lens of an עולה, olah,
the natural thing to do is look at this through the lens
of an עולה. olah. Here's an עולה olah that you're doing incorrectly.
Ah, you're doing an עולה olah in the wrong place! Ah, you're
doing it with the wrong thought! Right? I'm looking at it through
the עולה olah lens. But if I'm looking at it through the
עולה olah lens, I'm saying, but you haven't done מליקה melikah yet
because you've only got through one סימן. siman. So you're doing some
wrong things from the perspective of an עולה, olah, but you have
yet to do מליקה. melikah. Now, if I put a different lens
on it and I look through it through the חטאת chatas lens,
I would say, oh, here's a bird that you're doing in the
right place of a חטאת, chatas, for the sake of a חטאת,
chatas, and you just now did the מליקה melikah of a חטאת
chatas because you actually finished from a חטאת chatas perspective because that
was that one סימן. siman. So because the מליקה melikah of the
חטאת chatas took place before you yet did the מליקה melikah of
the עולה, olah, it's the moment in time that's critical. That designated
it as a חטאת. chatas. Meaning, it was able, the חטאת chatas
was able to step in, because the עולה olah designation, although it
was sanctified as an עולה, olah, its full status right as an
עולה olah did not yet take was effective, its full identity did
not yet take effect because it hasn't yet been שחט shachted as
an עולה. olah. So it's not just, oh, you did three חטאת
chatas things, if I treat you like all these ways like this
other thing, I'm magically going to make it. It's because the moment
of שחיטה, shechitah, the moment of מליקה, melikah, you have not yet
done from the עולה olah perspective, you have not yet done the
מליקת עולה. melikat olah. You haven't done the right thing. But from
the חטאת chatas perspective, here's a bird that was already מליקה melikah
in the place of a חטאת, chatas, for the sake of a
חטאת, chatas, and had a מליקה melikah like a חטאת. chatas. It
already took place. That is enough, that's enough of a gap for
it to step in the door and to redesignate it, to define
it as a חטאת. chatas. So it's what we said before, you
did all these חטאת chatas things, but it's specifically because the חטאת
chatas process finishes before the עולה olah process. Let's the חטאת chatas
like jump in that gap and define it before the עולה olah
had a מליקה melikah had a chance to define it. Yes?
Doesn't a חטאת chatas have to be for a specific sin?
Yes. So that is why it's not a kosher חטאת, chatas, well,
the גמרא's Gemara going to ask if it's a kosher חטאת. chatas.
Okay, but that is why, what do you call it, that is
why the basic point is it's enough of a חטאת chatas that
there's no מעילה. me'ilah. Maybe it can't be enough of a חטאת
chatas because it's not for a specific sin, you didn't designate it
as a חטאת, chatas, at the end of the day it wasn't
sanctified as a חטאת, chatas, but it was enough, got that identity
that there's now no longer מעילה. me'ilah. And presumably, and this isn't
explained, presumably the כהנים kohanim can eat the meat. Right? That's not
discussed either. So there's three issues here. Is there מעילה? me'ilah? Can
the כהנים kohanim eat the meat? Presumably if there's no מעילה, me'ilah,
the כהנים kohanim can eat the meat. The third thing is, do
you get credit for it as a חטאת? chatas? Okay, now you
getting credit for it as a חטאת, chatas, as you said, is
a bizarre idea, but let's take an example and the גמרא's Gemara
going to get to an example. Let's take an example that you
really did owe a חטאת. chatas. Okay. You came in and the
גמרא's Gemara example is going to be a woman, because this also
makes it better because if it's for a sin, you would have
to designate it presumably at the time of sanctification. But you could
bring a חטאת Chatas that's not about a sin, that's about ritual
cleansing, which according to some is what the word חטאת Chatas really
originally means. So if you're a woman that just had a baby,
you bring a bird for an עולה Olah and a bird for
a חטאת. Chatas. That's not for a sin, that's for a טהרה
Taharah process. So let's say you happen to be the woman and
you brought this עולה, Olah, they did it at the bottom, I'm
just anticipating what the גמרא Gemara is going to get to, in
theory you could say, okay, it can't count to atone for a
sin because it wasn't sanctified that way, but we just turned it
into a חטאת, Chatas, you owe a חטאת Chatas for part of
your ritual cleansing, let's call it a חטאת Chatas and that's part
of now your process of טהרה. Taharah. So the גמרא Gemara is
going to ask that question. But at this stage we're going to,
so it could be it's fully a חטאת, Chatas, okay, and in
some cases maybe that won't help if it's sin-related or whatever, but
maybe in some cases it will. But minimally, it's enough like a
חטאת Chatas and there's no מעילה. meilah. And presumably I would say
that means that the כהנים Kohanim could eat the meat.
Just saying there was a תוספות Tosafot on the משנה Mishnah at
the beginning of the מסכת masechet that said that אבל אם נתכפרו.
aval im nitkapru. הבא חטאת העוף haba Chatas HaOaf עשה למעלה כמעשה
כולן
פסולה,
asah lemalah kemaseh
kullan
pesulah, אף שעשה
עבודה כתיקנה והני באכילה,
af she-asah avodah ketiknah ve-hanei
be-achilah, אבל אם נתכפרו. aval im nitkapru.
So kind of assumes that the כפרה kapparah would...
Yes,
but that's a חטאת Chatas that you did like an עולה. Olah.
That's the reverse. Okay. All right. So now the גמרא Gemara says,
okay, so that's the, so that's like a nice sharpened explanation of
this. It wasn't just because you did everything like the other, right?
It was specifically because you, it, the חטאת Chatas designation jumped into
the gap. Okay.
Now the גמרא Gemara says like this, אי הכי, ei hachi, says
the גמרא, Gemara,
כיון שמלק בה סימן אחד נעשית חטאת העוף. keivan she-malak bah siman
echad naaseit Chatas HaOaf. It's made into a חטאת העוף. Chatas HaOaf.
So it wasn't just you did things differently, you specifically recategorized it,
and it wasn't just you did three ways of recategorizing it, but
that recategorization was able to jump into that gap. Okay, so אי
הכי ei hachi says the גמרא, Gemara, חטאת העוף נמי שעשה למעלה
כמעשה עולה, Chatas HaOaf nami she-asah lemalah kemaseh Olah, מכי מלק סימן
אחד תמשך ותהוי עולת העוף. miki malak siman echad timashech ve-tehei Olas
HaOaf. So the גמרא Gemara says like this, wait a minute, if
we're talking about getting something out of מעילה, meilah, I understand why
we're only talking about the עולה Olah turning it into a חטאת
Chatas because עולה Olah has מעילה meilah and a חטאת Chatas doesn't,
so you're going to give that scenario because our focus is did
you make it out of the מעילה meilah category. But the language
you just used that you say you turned it into a חטאת
Chatas suggests that it really becomes the other קרבן. korban. So if
that's true, says the גמרא, Gemara, why did we not give the
opposite example? You take your bird חטאת, Chatas, you do it above
in the place of an עולה Olah for the sake of an
עולה, Olah, and you cut both סימנים, simanim, and just say now
it's a כשר kosher עולה, Olah, okay? So why not go ahead?
Because what we say in the משנה Mishnah is that it's a
פסול חטאת pasul Chatas and whatever, חטאת Chatas done שלא לשמו shelo
lishmo you have to burn and get rid of etc. Why not
say it's a כשר kosher עולה Olah and you could offer it
up as an עולה? Olah? If you really mean it becomes the
new קרבן, korban, not, it's not just a מעילה meilah issue, okay?
So why didn't you give that example? So the גמרא Gemara says,
why don't we say that? חטאת העוף נמי שעשה למעלה כמעשה עולה,
Chatas HaOaf nami she-asah lemalah kemaseh Olah, מכי מלק בה סימן אחד
תמשך ותהוי עולת העוף. miki malak bah siman echad timashech ve-tehei Olas
HaOaf.
Now it's a funny סברא sevara that says once it was מלק
סימן אחד, malak siman echad, because really you should have said two
סימנים. simanim. סימן אחד siman echad you're still treating it like a
חטאת. Chatas. So it's a funny הוה אמינא hava amina even at
that line. Okay. So anyway, but the גמרא Gemara says like this,
so the גמרא Gemara says וכי תימא הכי נמי, ve-chi teima hachi
nami, maybe that's true. Maybe if you did everything above you turned
it into an עולה. Olah. Or maybe the גמרא Gemara thinks once
you did one סימן siman and from the חטאת Chatas lens we're
saying oh it's above and it's not for the sake of a
חטאת Chatas we can't call it a חטאת, Chatas, but we can
call it an עולה. Olah. The גמרא Gemara hasn't really understood that
the סימן אחד siman echad was that critical gap. Okay. The גמרא
Gemara still is sort of understanding if you do everything like a
חטאת Chatas then the עולה Olah becomes a חטאת, Chatas, so if
you do everything like an עולה Olah the חטאת Chatas should become
an עולה. Olah. So the גמרא Gemara says, and if you say
that's true, והאמר רבי יוחנן משום רבי בניה, ve-ha-amar Rebbi Yochanan mishum
Rebbi Benayah, כך היא הצעה של משנה, kach hi hatzaah shel Mishnah,
doesn't רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan say in the name of רבי בניה,
Rebbi Benayah, this is the laying out of the משנה. Mishnah. Now
what does that mean? So the גמרא Gemara assumes what it means
is our משנה Mishnah gives one example for רבי יהושע. Rebbi Yehoshua.
The example was
an עולה Olah that you did as a חטאת. Chatas. So somebody
comes and says, this is the exact sort of framing of the
משנה. Mishnah. So what does that mean? Presumably it means this is
the only case they argue on, like it's exact precisely this is
their debate. So מאי לאו, mai lav, doesn't it mean כך הצעה
ותו לא, kach hatzaah ve-tu lo, this is their debate, an עולה
Olah that you did below as a חטאת Chatas and they're not
debating the other case? לא, lo, says the גמרא, Gemara, maybe not.
Maybe he means כך הצעה של כולם. kach hatzaah shel kullam. Maybe
he means כהאי אצא דכולה משנה. kehai atza dechula mishnah. Maybe he
means this debate of theirs is really relevant to the whole משנה.
Mishnah. You could read it two ways. This, this is the משנה.
Mishnah. This is the משנה Mishnah meaning it's exactly the way it's
said and they're only debating this case, or you could read it
to say this issue they're debating is really both all the cases
of the משנה. Mishnah. All right, so anyway, so the גמרא Gemara
says, so what's the logic? Don't say to me because of that
line of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan this isn't the possibility. I really
think based on what you said, logically, if a חטאת chatas can
become, if an עולה olah can be a חטאת, chatas, then a
חטאת chatas could be an עולה. olah. So why not? So the
גמרא Gemara said, no. רב אשי אמר, Rav Ashi amar, no, no,
no, that the logic doesn't work. It is very specifically this
direction. בשלמא עולת העוף שעשאה למטה כמעשה חטאת, Bishlama olas ha'of she'asah
lemata kema'aseh chatas, if
you do the bird עולה olah below like a חטאת, chatas, לשם
חטאת, leshaim chatas, כיון דהאי הכשרה בסימן אחד והאי הכשרה בשני סימנים,
keivan dehai hachshirah besiman echad vehai hachshirah beshnei simanim,
and I'd already jumped ahead and told you this explanation. But it
wasn't just that, oh, you can recategorize. It's specifically about that critical
point in time. When you're doing the עולה olah below as a
חטאת, chatas, it finishes the act of a חטאת chatas before it
finishes the act of an עולה. olah. The one סימן siman gets
cut before the two סימנים simanim gets cut. ועולת העוף למטה ליתא.
Ve'olas ha'of lemata leisa. So here you are, you cut one סימן,
siman, you've done the act of a חטאת, chatas, you have yet
to do the act of an עולה. olah. There's no such logic
as an עולה olah at the bottom of the מזבח. mizbe'ach. So
כיון דמליק בסימן אחד נמשכת ונעשית חטאת העוף, keivan demalik besiman echad
nimshechet vena'aseit chatas of,
you jumped into that gap. You're doing everything like a חטאת, chatas,
and now you've even finished the שחיטה shechitah of a חטאת. chatas.
So therefore, even though it started as an עולה, olah, you were
able to turn it into a חטאת chatas before it had a
complete, with the identity of an עולה, olah, because it hasn't yet
been מליקה meliked as an עולה. olah. And that gap let you
redefine it. Okay. אלא חטאת
העוף
כיון דאמר מר מליקה בכל מקום כשירה,
Ella chatas
of keivan de'amar mar melika bechol makom kesheirah,
so if you're doing a bird חטאת chatas above, so he says,
so there you are, you're doing it above. Now, a bird חטאת,
chatas, the מליקה melika can be done at the top of the
altar. Doing the מליקה melika at the top of the altar does
not by definition mean you're treating it like an עולה. olah. In,
you could actually in theory do the מליקה melika of a חטאת
chatas at the top. You have to do the, excuse me, אלא
חטאת העוף, Ella chatas of, wait a minute, what are you doing?
Yeah, the חטאת העוף, chatas of, you could do, in theory, although
the sprinkling of the חטאת העוף chatas of goes below, in theory
you could do the מליקה melika at the top. So when you
do, when you do the עולת העוף olas ha'of atop and you
do it below, you're doing everything like a חטאת, chatas, and the
definition jumps in at the cutting of one סימן. siman. When you're
doing a חטאת העוף chatas of above, there's two reasons why that
doesn't get to be redefined. One is just that you're doing the
מליקה melika above is not, I'm not so impressed with that, by
that alone, because technically even as a חטאת, chatas, kosher to do
the מליקה melika above, just make sure you do the sprinkling below.
So that's not totally identifying it as an עולה. olah. Now the
same could be said in reverse. But the second point is the
more critical, is that you don't define it, its definition, this thing,
you know, this, once you cut one סימן, siman, you've already defined
it as a חטאת. chatas. So you don't get to redefine it
as an עולה. olah. The עולה olah definition is later than the
חטאת chatas definition above. Right? You get it? When you do the
עולה olah above and you do it below, the new definition of
the חטאת chatas kicks in first, because you slaughtered one סימן siman
and it kicked in first. When you do the חטאת chatas below,
above, the new definition of an עולה olah doesn't kick in first,
because treating it like an עולה olah requires cutting the second סימן.
siman. So it's still the old definition of a חטאת chatas that
kicks in once you cut one סימן, siman, and even the location
is not inappropriate as a חטאת chatas when you're above. So there
the חטאת chatas definition is going to remain. All right. אלא חטאת
העוף כיון דאמר מר מליקה בכל מקום כשירה מכדי מליק בסימן אחד
איסלא. Ella chatas of keivan de'amar mar melika bechol makom kesheirah michdei
malik besiman echad issala.
So you cut one סימן, siman, you're now made it a חטאת
chatas and it's שלא לשמו, shelo lishmo, you're thinking of it as
an עולה, olah, and it's even in the place theoretically of a
חטאת. chatas. So what it becomes is a חטאת פסולה. chatas pesulah.
It doesn't become an
עולה. olah. כי הדר מליק
באידך סימן היכי מימשכה והויא עולת העוף, Ki hadar malik be'idach siman
heichi mimshacha vehavya olas ha'of, how do you get to redefine it?
You've already made it a חטאת פסולה. chatas pesulah. So again, it's
not so clear to me why the גמרא Gemara is emphasizing that
the place is okay above. The real point is the difference between
one סימן siman and two סימנים, simanim, right? Which is that, which
is that, which is that, which is that, which definition jumps in
first. If it's an עולה olah doing it above, below as a
חטאת, chatas, before, when you got to one סימן, siman, you've already
redefined it as a חטאת chatas and all the context is a
חטאת chatas before its natural definition of an עולה olah gets to
be reinforced. And therefore the חטאת chatas definition finds the
gap. When you do an עולה olah which
belongs below, excuse me, when you do a חטאת chatas which belongs
below and you do it up as an עולה, olah, okay, when
you cut one סימן, siman, okay, you've now reaffirmed its old definition,
its standard definition as a חטאת chatas and it's a חטאת פסולה.
chatas pesulah. And that's... That is the definition that stays with it
before your attempt of a new definition gets an opportunity to jump
in. Okay, so that's why it is very specifically here, this is
where it has the gap, this is where you get to redefine
it. If you're doing an עולה olah below, you cut that one
סימן, siman, boom, that was your opening to define it as a
חטאת.
chatas. Any limitation between the one and the two?
No, it's like, you know, it could be a split second, but
it doesn't matter.
How long could it be?
In other words, it doesn't matter. It, you know, we slow down,
we go frame by frame, we slow down, you know what I
mean? Just even if it's in that millisecond, okay, it was in
that millisecond that it got redefined. It doesn't matter in theory whether
you were actually pausing and stopping or whatever.
I mean if he waited half a minute and then did the
second one.
No, that the גמרא gemara discussed before, whether שהייה shehiya invalidates by
a, you know, by an עולת העוף. olas ha-of. But that's not
relevant. He, whether you did or didn't slow down, it was in
that one frame, that one one-thousandth of a second that it got
defined, it got redefined as a חטאת. chatas. That was the gap
for it to get redefined as a חטאת chatas before it could
get defined as an עולה. olah. Okay, or defined as a חטאת,
chatas, yeah, redefined. Okay, so the גמרא gemara says like this: גופא.
gufa. All right, so now we understand רבי יהושע's Rebbe Yehoshua's position.
It's making more and more sense by the minute. So גופא, gufa,
אמר רב אדא בר אהבה, amar Rav Adda bar Ahava, אומר היה
רבי יהושע, omer haya Rebbe Yehoshua, רבי יהושע Rebbe Yehoshua used to
say, עולת העוף שעשאה למטה כמעשה חטאת לשם חטאת כיוון שמלק בה
סימן אחד נמשכת ונעשית חטאת העוף. olas ha-of she-asa-ah lemata ke-ma'aseh chatas
leshem chatas keivan she-malak bah siman echad nimsheches ve-na'asis chatas ha-of. That's
what we just said. Okay? You're doing it below, you've got, you're
doing everything like the חטאת, chatas, the place of the חטאת, chatas,
the intent of a חטאת, chatas, and that one סימן, siman, you've
now made it into, you've done the מליקה melika of a חטאת,
chatas, and therefore the new categorization takes hold because it's not yet
competing with the מליקה melika of the עולה. olah. That hasn't happened
yet. תא שמע, ta shema, come in here. Okay, חטאת זו. chatas
zu. Now, for all those who remembered last time we did קדשים,
kodshim, you know, seven years ago, the very end of קדשים, kodshim,
we get to do קינים, kinnim, we get to do the משניות
mishnayos of קינים, kinnim, which are some of the most difficult משניות,
mishnayos, you know, in all of ש"ס. shas. And basically, they and
so so the קינים kinnim is about bird sacrifices and it's about
interesting like mathematical permutations. And if therefore you were saying I just
wish there were some גמרא gemara on קינים kinnim because I loved
it so much I wanted to get a little bit more into
it, here's your opportunity because what we're going to do now to
analyze this is to get into some משניות mishnayos of קינים. kinnim.
And basically what we're going to do is the following: we're going
to prove, or we're assuming and we're going to demonstrate later, that
קינים kinnim was written, the סתם stam of קינים, kinnim, the editor
of קינים kinnim as it were, is רבי יהושע. Rebbe Yehoshua. Okay,
remember רבי יהושע Rebbe Yehoshua here is the one now that's very
interesting. Here we're talking about רבי יהושע Rebbe Yehoshua being of the
position that a bird עולה, olah, if you treat it like a
bird like a חטאת, chatas, can become a חטאת. chatas. And רבי
יהושע Rebbe Yehoshua is the author of קינים, kinnim, which is all
about bird sacrifices.
And the other thing about קינים kinnim is basically like this: it
mostly deals with women who are bringing their bird sacrifices because of
childbirth. That again gives the גמרא gemara a nice opportunity to discuss
these mathematical permutations. And there the following it deals with examples like
you have Sarah and Rachel, and they both just decide, hey, we
both gave birth at the same time, let's go bring our bird
sacrifices at the same time. A woman who gives childbirth brings a
bird חטאת chatas and a bird עולה. olah. So they buy, you
know, I don't know, four birds together and they give it to
the כהן, kohen, and the כהן kohen doesn't know whose is whose,
and he brings them in different places, and who still has to
bring a קרבן? korban? Like those are the questions, okay? Or Sarah
has her קרבנות korbanos and Leah has hers, and then they mix
them up and the כהן kohen doesn't know, and it deals with
all those theories. Now one of the key things that you have
to know about this is
is that you can wait for some of the designations of the
identity of the קרבנות. korbanos. So you could go ahead and buy
two birds, and at that time you could say this is my
חטאת chatas and this is my עולה, olah, okay, or you could
just say give both two birds to the כהן, kohen, and then
it'll be defined which is the חטאת chatas and which is the
עולה olah based on where they're brought on the מזבח, mizbe'ach, okay?
You could also say, hey, you know,
let's go ahead you and me, Rachel and Leah, whatever, and we'll
buy two birds, we'll buy four birds together, and we could say
these two are the חטאות chataos and these two are the עולות,
olos, but we could wait in terms of designating whose is whose,
and that would be designated by the כהן. kohen. So some of
the designation could be get done by how what the כהן kohen
is thinking or doing, you know, when he's bringing it. Okay, so
that's like another important point you have to know about קינים. kinnim.
And the final point you have to know is
is that while a the obligatory bird, two birds that are brought
is a חטאת chatas and an עולה, olah, if somebody makes a
נדר neder to bring a bird sacrifice, okay, then they can go
ahead, they cannot actually bring just one, we actually learned that earlier,
but but whatever they bring, one, two, or twenty, you can only
bring an עולה olah as a נדר. neder. You can't bring a
חטאת chatas as a נדר. neder. Okay, so that's some of the
background. So what we're going to do is now we're going to
put forward some of these משניות mishnayos in קינים kinnim and we're
going to say it doesn't look from here that from that רבי
יהושע Rebbe Yehoshua if you do an עולה olah if you treat
it... עולה Olah below as a חטאת Chatas you would really turn
it into a חטאת, Chatas, because we're going to have a scenario
where we're going to take in קינים Kinnim a woman's עולה, Olah,
we're going to do it below as a חטאת, Chatas, and if
you really did redefine it, that woman should get credit for bringing
her חטאת. Chatas. Now David before said wait, how could it count
as a חטאת Chatas doesn't have to be sin related? Here's a
case where חטאת Chatas doesn't have to be sin related. As long
as I brought רחל'ס Rachel's bird and now it has a new
definition as a חטאת, Chatas, right, רחל Rachel should have she had
an obligation of a חטאת, Chatas, this should have satisfied it. So
this is going to be an opportunity to test, did רבי יהושע
Rabbi Yehoshua really mean it gets really turns into a חטאת Chatas
or just enough for the laws of מעילה? Meilah? Okay, so let's
take a look. תא שמע, Ta Shma, come in here.
חטאת לזו ועולה לזו. Chatas l'zo v'Olah l'zo. Okay, so you have
a case basically
where
רחל Rachel and לאה Leah both had childbirth. You know, one brought
one of their קרבנות Korbanot and the other brought also one of
her קרבנות. Korbanot. At this stage, רחל Rachel still needs to bring
a חטאת Chatas and לאה Leah still needs to bring an עולה.
Olah. Okay, that's what's left of their obligation. And the כהן Kohen
goes ahead and he basically and they bring it to the כהן.
Kohen. And they say, here are our birds, okay? But
and one of those birds was רחל'ס Rachel's חטאת Chatas and one
was לאה'ס Leah's עולה. Olah. But they didn't tell the כהן Kohen
which was which or they did tell the כהן Kohen and he
forgot and he made a mistake and he didn't know which and
he just did one above and one below. But he didn't know
if he got it right or he got it wrong. Got it?
So one of these is a חטאת, Chatas, one's an עולה Olah
and he mixed them up and we don't know which he did
and which in which place. Okay, so עשה שתיהם למעלה, asa shteihem
l'mala, if he did both of the birds above, מחצה כשר מחצה
פסול. mechtza kasher mechtza pasul. So okay, you got the עולה Olah
right, you got the חטאת Chatas wrong. So the woman who was
obligated in an עולה, Olah, she got credit. The woman who was
obligated in a חטאת, Chatas, you did her bird wrong and she's
going to have to bring another bird. שתיהם למטה, shteihem l'mata, if
you did them both below, so מחצה כשר מחצה פסול. mechtza kasher
mechtza pasul. The woman who was obligated in a חטאת, Chatas, her
bird was done right, whichever one of the two it was, and
the woman who was obligated in an עולה, Olah, her bird was
done wrong and she still has to bring an עולה. Olah. Okay,
אחת למעלה ואחת למטה, achas l'mala v'achas l'mata,
that's of course the worst case, right? If you split them up,
okay, then you could get them both wrong. שתיהן פסולות. shteihen pesulot.
We have to assume that neither woman fulfilled her obligation. שאני אומר
she'ani omer because I'm going to say חטאת קריבה למעלה ועולה קריבה
למטה, Chatas k'reiva l'mala v'Olah k'reiva l'mata, maybe you did the חטאת
Chatas above and the עולה Olah below, you did them both wrong
and therefore neither woman fulfills her obligation. So now the גמרא'ס Gemara's
got a question, okay, which is a very good one. ניהי נמי
דעולה קריבה למטה, nihi nami d'Olah k'reiva l'mata, here is the woman
who's let's say it's true, the woman whose עולה Olah bird the
עולה, Olah, her bird was done below rather than above. But if
קינים Kinnim is according to רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua, so what? Let
it turn into a חטאת. Chatas. Now she's now the okay, ניהי
נמי דעולה קריבה למטה תימשך ותהא חטאת העוף, nihi nami d'Olah k'reiva
l'mata timashech v'tehei chatas ha-of,
let it turn into a חטאת, Chatas, okay, right, you got it,
she brought an עולה, Olah, it was done below, big deal according
to רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua, turn it into a חטאת. Chatas. So
now the גמרא'ס Gemara's going to say, wait a minute, but she's
not obligated in a חטאת, Chatas, לאה Leah the other woman is
obligated in a חטאת, Chatas, right? אימא דאמר רבי יהושע בחד גברא,
eima d'amar Rabbi Yehoshua b'chad gavra, if it's one person, so if
you were to turn my עולה Olah into a חטאת Chatas and
I was obligated in a חטאת, Chatas, then fine, I would get
credit as a חטאת. Chatas. That would make sense. But בתרי גברי
מי אמר? bitrei gavri mi amar? Here the woman who's obligated in
an עולה, Olah, her עולה Olah became a חטאת. Chatas. That doesn't
do her any good, okay? So now it might not do any
good but the animal might still be כשר, kosher, okay, but the
גמרא Gemara is basically you know, it's not exactly clear which line
the גמרא Gemara is drawing, but the גמרא Gemara still might be
saying, you know, if it can't be if you're not obligated in
a חטאת, Chatas, it can't become your חטאת. Chatas. So maybe that
case the whole thing is פסול. pasul. The redesignation maybe only works
or you know, or the certainly the possibility that you know, that
it actually fulfills a person's obligation, but maybe even the whole redesignation
only works if this חטאת Chatas works for you. In this case
the חטאת Chatas doesn't work for you, the חטאת Chatas only works
is for לאה, Leah, not for רחל. Rachel. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara says okay, but I'm let's give I'm going to give
you the next level משנה, Mishnah, which is actually going to be
a case where actually the woman was obligated in a חטאת Chatas
and we're still going to see the עולה Olah won't become her
חטאת. Chatas. Let's take a look. תא שמע, Ta Shma, come in
here, okay. חטאת ועולה וסתומה ומפורשת. Chatas v'Olah v'stuma u'meforeshet.
You got the two women, okay, basically they are both obligated in
a קרבן korban and a half. Okay, basically what happens is is
that לאה Leah is רחל'ס Rachel's obligated in a חטאת, Chatas, לאה'ס
Leah's obligated in an עולה, Olah, that's for their first childbirth. Wait
let me just reread רש״י Rashi make sure I'm getting this right.
Wait a minute. חטאת ועולה וסתומה ומפורשת. Chatas v'Olah v'stuma u'meforeshet. Hold
on hold on.
Okay.
Right, so basically here's the story. Two women both had two childbirths,
okay? They had a baby last year, one of them brought half
her co—one of them brought a חטאת Chatos *Chatas* and an עולה
Olah *Olah*, and the other brought an עולה Olah *Olah* and a
חטאת Chatos, *Chatas*, okay? So and then this year... hold on, wait,
let me just one more time, hold on, let me just make
sure I got this right. One more time.
Right, right, okay, fine. Okay, so here's the story. Okay, so
here's
רחל *Rachel* and לאה *Leah*. So last year, this was birth number
one, okay? Birth number one. So last year, okay, they were both
obligated in a חטאת Chatos, *Chatas* and an עולה Olah *Olah*.
Okay, so she brought her עולה Olah *Olah* and she brought her
חטאת Chatos, *Chatas*. So רחל *Rachel* still owes an עולה Olah. *Olah*
and לאה *Leah* still owes a חטאת Chatos *Chatas*, okay? Got it?
And now you have birth number two. So she owes now a
חטאת Chatos, *Chatas* and an עולה Olah. *Olah*, and she owes now
a חטאת Chatos *Chatas* and an עולה Olah, *Olah*. Okay, so between
them they owe three sets: חטאת Chatos עולה Olah, *Chatas Olah*, חטאת
Chatos, עולה Olah? *Chatas Olah*, חטאת Chatos, עולה Olah, *Chatas Olah*. You
got it? This one owes two עולות Olas *Olos* and a חטאת
Chatos *Chatas*, and this one owes two חטאות Chatoses *Chataos* and an
עולה Olah *Olah*. All right? So that's what they owe. Now what
they decide to do is, hey, between us we owe three sets
of birds, let's go ahead and buy three sets of birds. So
they buy three sets of birds. Each set they split up in
a different way, okay? So here's what they do. Okay. חטאת Chatos.
ועולה וסתומה ומפורשת
*Chatas vaOlah uStumah uMefureshet*. One set they say, okay, set number
one, this will be your חטאת Chatos? *Chatas* and my עולה Olah
*Olah*, okay? That was set number one. That's, okay. So set number
one they say this is your חטאת Chatos. *Chatas* and this is
my עולה Olah. *Olah*. They designate that, okay? This is, I don't
know, לאה *Leah*'s חטאת Chatos. *Chatas* and רחל *Rachel*'s עולה Olah, *Olah*.
That's set number one, that's חטאת Chatos. ועולה *Chatas vaOlah*. Set number
two is סתומה Stuma, *Stumah*. סתומה stuma. *Stumah* means that we're going
to let the כהן kohen, *Kohen* decide. Okay, it's a חטאת Chatos.
עולה Olah *Chatas Olah*, we're not saying which is a חטאת Chatos,
*Chatas*, which is an עולה Olah *Olah*, we're not saying whose is
whose. It's based on what the כהן kohen *Kohen* does. סתומה *Stumah*
means unexplicit, okay? So here we have sort of in the Heideggerian
sort of state,
okay? Okay, the, okay, that's going to be, we'll figure out whose
is whose, okay? And set number three
is
מפורשת *Mefureshet*. Is we actually say חטאת Chatos, *Chatas* and עולה Olah
*Olah*, okay, but we don't say whose is whose. One is a
חטאת Chatos *Chatas*, one is an עולה Olah, *Olah*, but which one
counts for רחל *Rachel* and which one counts for לאה *Leah*, we're
going to let the כהן kohen *Kohen* figure it out. Now to
some degree that makes sense because the only way in which they
differ is that one needs, meaning they're generally the same, they both
need a חטאת Chatos. עולה Olah חטאת Chatos. עולה Olah *Chatas Olah
Chatas Olah*, but רחל *Rachel* needs a specific extra עולה Olah *Olah*
and לאה *Leah* needs a specific extra חטאת Chatos. *Chatas*. So this
set, let's split it up. This will be my חטאת Chatos? *Chatas*,
this will be your עולה olah *Olah*. These other two sets we'll
let the כהן *Kohen* figure it out. We each of us needs
a חטאת chatat *Chatas* and an עולה olah *Olah* from those other
two sets. The problem is here they totally said let them figure
it out all together. Here they already for whatever reason designated one
bird as a חטאת chatat? *Chatas* and one bird as an עולה
olah *Olah* but they didn't say whose was whose. So this is
just a situation ripe for disaster, okay? So, okay, so which is
which?
The סתומה ומפורשת *Stumah uMefureshet*?
Right. So this is the סתומה *Stumah*, okay?
And I believe רש"י *Rashi* said this is the—I believe רש"י *Rashi*
said this is the מפורשת *Mefureshet* because you designated חטאת chatat, *Chatas*
and עולה olah, *Olah* but you didn't designate whose was whose. And
this is the one that's being called חטאת chatat ועולה *Chatas vaOlah*,
which means that you've fully said this is לאה *Leah*'s חטאת chatat
*Chatas*, that's רחל *Rachel*'s עולה olah, *Olah*. Here you didn't say which
bird was which, here you said which bird was a חטאת chatat.
*Chatas*, which bird was an עולה olah. *Olah*, but you didn't say
it was whose was whose, okay?
Okay,
so let's take a look. חטאת chatat, ועולה וסתומה ומפורשת *Chatas vaOlah
uStumah uMefureshet*. עשה כולן למעלה *Asah kullan lemala*. Now the כהן *Kohen*
goes ahead and does all of them at the top of the
altar. He treats all of them like an עולה olah. *Olah*. Okay,
so obviously what's the הלכה halacha *halacha*? So now you don't have
to worry about this complication, just think about it. He treats them
all like an עולה olah. *Olah*. So all the עולות Olas, *Olos*
are כשר Kosher. *Kasher*. Okay, so that's easy. Okay, so all of—they've
both satisfied their עולה olah, *Olah* obligation. רחל *Rachel* satisfies her extra
עולה olah, *Olah* obligation and then everybody just has to, you know,
she has to bring one חטאת chatat *Chatas* and she has to
bring two. Okay, you did it above, all the עולות Olas. *Olos*
in the mix are כשר Kosher *Kasher*. Okay. עשה כולן למעלה *Asah
kullan lemala* מחצה כשר *Mechtza Kasher*. Okay, half of them are כשר
and half are פסול, Pasul, which basically means all the עולות olot.
in the group were good and all the חטאות Chatoses weren't good.
So everybody who was required an עולה olah fulfilled their עולה olah
obligation. All the חטאות have to be rebrought, brought. כולן למטה, Kulam
l'mata, you did it below. מחצה כשר, מחצה פסול. Mechtza kasher, mechtza
pasul. All the חטאת chatat, obligations were good, okay, but all the
עולה olah. obligations were not good. So anybody that's obligated in an
עולה olah has to rebring their עולה. olah. If you obligated in
two עולות, olot, rebring your two עולות. olot, Fine, okay. Now, the
worst case is חצי למעלה וחצי למטה, Chetzi l'ma'ala v'chetzi l'mata, half
above, half below. Now, we could really make it really worse and
just say any random half above. But we're going to actually say
that no, somehow magically, what he did was he knew to split
each set, okay? So in each set he did half of each
set above and half of each set below, okay? You got it?
It's not like any random split. Okay, each set half was above,
half was below. All right? So in each set, though, it's possible
that he got it reversed. Okay, and so here, if he got
it reversed, they're both invalid, right? Because this is a חטאת, chatat.
this is an עולה. olah And if he got it reversed, he
got it reversed. Here, one is a חטאת, chatat one is an
עולה, olah. if he got it reversed, they're both invalid. Here, you
can't reverse it. It's dealer's choice, Cohen's choice. So this קרבן Korban
was כשר. Okay, if he split it up, okay, one became a
חטאת, chatat, one became an עולה, olah and these two don't count.
Okay, good? All right. So
אינה כשירה אלא סתומה, Eina k'shira ela stuma, the only one that's
כשר is the סתומה, is the unexplicated one, מתחלקת ביניהם, mit'chaleket beneihem,
and they split it. Meaning, you know, now what does it mean
they split it? Because who, who got the חטאת chatat. and who
got the עולה? olah. So whatever, they make stipulations, okay, how you
figure out מתחלקת ביניהם. mit'chaleket beneihem. There was a good חטאת, chatat,
a good עולה, we don't know whose חטאת chatat it accounted for
and whose עולה it accounted for, so we'll bring another two קרבנות
Korbanot and we'll sort of, and we'll make some stipulation. I don't
want to get into the etcetera, but you get the idea. Okay,
somehow a חטאת and an עולה worked and we'll figure out and,
you know, for one of us, you know, one of us got
one, one got the other, we'll figure out how to make a
stipulation to make it all that we get credit. Okay, but at
least there was credit for the חטאת, one חטאת, one עולה. But
now the גמרא Gemara has a question: why, when you did this,
if you reversed it, so you totally ruined her חטאת and her
עולה, but here it doesn't say whose is whose. And if you
reversed it, okay, so what? So you did the עולה below as
a חטאת. According to רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua, what happens if you
do an עולה below as a חטאת? It becomes a חטאת. And
you say, oh, but you can't make it count for somebody else's
חטאת. I don't need it to count for somebody else's חטאת. We
don't have a designation whose is whose here. So this עולה became
a חטאת. So one of these women should get credit for a
חטאת, okay? So why not? Okay, so, so ואילו, V'ilu, so the
גמרא Gemara says, ואילו מפורשים לא, V'ilu m'furashim lo, but the case
of מפורשים M'furashim where you designated one as a חטאת, one as
an עולה, but you didn't say whose is whose, nobody's getting credit.
ואמאי, V'amai, why not? נהי נמי דעולה קרבה למטה, Nehi nami d'ola
karva l'mata,
it's true that an עולה goes, was being brought below, but according
to רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua תימשך ותהא חטאת העוף, Timashech v'tehei chatas
ha'of, let it become a חטאת and it's... and you can't say
oh, it's a different person's חטאת. No, it hasn't been designated. One
of these women should get credit for a חטאת. וכי תימא הא
דלא רבי יהושע, V'chi teima ha d'lo Rabbi Yehoshua, so that's a
really good question. So now the, the only pushback is maybe who
says this משנה's Mishna going according to רבי יהושע? Rabbi Yehoshua? If
we're going according to רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua, the עולה should get
credit for a חטאת. So the גמרא Gemara says וכי תימא הא
דלא רבי יהושע, V'chi teima ha d'lo Rabbi Yehoshua, maybe who says
קינין Kinim is according to רבי יהושע? Rabbi Yehoshua? Maybe not. לא
מצית אמרת הכי, Lo matzat amrat hachi, ומי מצית אמרת הכי, U'mi
matzat amrat hachi, you can't say that. And now what the גמרא's
Gemara going to do is going to bring in a long משנה
Mishna in קינין, Kinim, an even more complicated משנה Mishna in קינין,
Kinim, to get to the end of the משנה Mishna which makes
it sound like רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua is the סתם Stam author,
okay, of קינין, Kinim, and therefore we're going to prove that רבי
יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua is the author of קינין, Kinim, so if that's
true, why did this not get to count, the עולה that was
below, why did it not get to count as a חטאת? So
what I'm going to do is I'm going to cheat here for
a minute because I want to finish the train of thought and
then we're going to, it's going to take us half of tomorrow's
דף Daf is also figuring out this difficult משנה. Mishna. I'm just
going to jump to the end of the answer at the end
so you sort of see the arc. Okay, and then we're going
to go back and figure out that משנה. Mishna. So it's going
to quote a big משנה Mishna here in קינין, Kinim, and the
punchline of the משנה Mishna turns to ס"ח ע"א, Samech ches amud
alef, okay, and
on ס"ח ע"א Samech ches amud alef it says the following: אמר
רבי יהושע, Amar Rabbi Yehoshua, like six lines in. Okay, so this
is the end of this complicated משנה. Mishna. אמר רבי יהושע, Amar
Rabbi Yehoshua, says רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua, זהו שאמרו, Zehu she'amru, oh,
this ruling that we've now just given, that's what they said when
they meant when they said כשהוא חי קולו אחד, כשהוא מת קולו
שבעה. K'shehu chai kol echad, k'shehu mes kolo shiva. That when an
animal's alive you hear one sound from it and when it's dead,
like a cow, you're able to turn it into all these different
things, a horn, you know, you use the intestines to make stringed
instruments, etcetera, etcetera. So we'll worry about all that later. The point
for us is that he basically ends the משנה Mishna and says
זהו שאמרו. Zehu she'amru. אמרו amru and he's sort of talking, you
know, like the narrator. Like, you know what I mean? He's not
just, it's sort of like saying, he's sort of like saying, ah,
now you understand what we mean when we say or whatever, so
somehow the גמרא Gemara hears that voice of רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua
not just like a משנה Mishnah quoting רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua but
רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua like wrapping it all up, okay, speaking as
a narrator.
And that's what רבי אליעזר שמותי Rabbi Eliezer Shmuta'i used to, you
wouldn't, maybe, maybe, but anyway, but for us this shows that רבי
יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua is the author of קינים. Kinim. So if רבי
יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua is the author of קינים, Kinim, goes back to
our question, why doesn't the עולה that's done below, the עולה that's
done below, at least count as a חטאת and one of the
women get credit? And the גמרא's Gemara's answer is, אימא דאמר רבי
יהושע, Eima d'amar Rabbi Yehoshua, when did רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua say
that an עולה becomes a חטאת? לאפוקי מידי מעילה. L'apokei mi'yadei me'ilah.
He didn't really mean it becomes a חטאת, at the end of
the day it's an עולה, but it was so designated as a
חטאת that you can't say מעילה me'ilah applies to it anymore. Okay?
But למיסק ליה לחובה מי אמר? L'misak lei l'chova mi amar? He
never said really you fulfilled your obligation with it. Okay, so this
bottom line is sort of the clarification. רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua says
it gets redesignated, but in the משנה Mishnah he just said you
get out of מעילה. me'ilah. The גמרא Gemara by defining it, look,
you did everything like a חטאת and you even jumped into that
little gap that was created before it got to be an עולה,
and the language used in the גמרא, Gemara, not in the משנה,
Mishnah, was it becomes a חטאת. And now the גמרא's Gemara's pulling
back and saying, okay, maybe it doesn't really become a חטאת, it's
enough of a חטאת that there's no מעילה. me'ilah. Again, what's not
being answered is, and I think needs to go along with this
is, and the כהנים kohanim get to eat the meat. That's an
interesting question. But it is not, at the end of the day,
it was sanctified as an עולה. So it doesn't get to be
fully redefined as a חטאת, and that's why here neither of the
women get credit, because even though it's no longer מעילה me'ilah and
maybe the כהנים kohanim can eat it, it doesn't count for anybody's
חטאת. Okay, so that's where we're going to get. Now let's go
back and read the משנה Mishnah that we skipped over, which we'll
start today and end tomorrow, which is this more complicated משנה Mishnah
in קינים. Kinim. I think it's the last משנה Mishnah in קינים
Kinim if memory serves. Okay, so תא שמע, ta shma, let's go
back to the גמרא. Gemara. האישה שאמרה הרי עלי קן אם אלד
זכר, Ha'ishah she'amrah harei alai kan im eiled zachar, okay,
קן, kan, I think it's actually קן ציפור, kan tzipor, קן סמיכה.
kan smicha. האישה שאמרה הרי עלי קן אם אלד זכר. Ha'ishah she'amrah
harei alai kan im eiled zachar. I accept upon myself to bring
two birds if I give birth to a male. Okay now, again,
when a woman makes a נדר, neder, anybody makes a נדר neder
to bring birds, they're always going to be עולה. Okay, so she's
obligating herself in two עולות. olot Okay, ילדה זכר, yaldah zachar, now
she gives birth to a male, so she has to satisfy her
vow. מביאה שתי קינין, mavia shtei kinin, she brings two sets. אחד
לנדרה ואחד לחובתה, echad l'nidrah v'echad l'chovatah, one to satisfy her נדר,
neder, which is both of which are going to be עולות, olot.
and one for her obligation as a woman who gave birth, which
is one is a חטאת and one is an
עולה. Now נתנתן לכהן, netanatan l'kohen, okay, she gives them to the
כהן, and she hasn't designated which is the חטאת, which is the
עולה, whatever, it's all, like I said, dealer's choice. If you don't
designate, the כהן gets to designate. So צריך לעשות שלושה למעלה ואחת
למטה. tzarich la'asot shlosha l'ma'alah v'achat l'matah. The כהן has to do
three above, because three of them are עולות, olot. and one below,
one is a חטאת. לא עשה כן, lo asah chen, he didn't
do that. אלא עשה שניים למעלה ושניים למטה. ela asah shnayim l'ma'alah
u'shnayim l'matah. He assumed she had two childbirths. A woman comes and
brings you two sets of birds, pretty reasonable thing to assume that
this is going to be for two childbirths. She doesn't say, this
is the חטאת, this is an עולה, so again, a pretty reasonable
thing to assume would be she's leaving it to be for dealer's
choice. She's making it unexplicated. I get to define which is which.
So from each set, he does one above and one below. Okay?
So now the problem here isn't that he went against her designation.
The problem here is is that she was obligated in three עולות
olot and he only brought two of them above. Okay, so of
the set B, we'll call it set A, okay, it's not designated,
okay,
right?
They're both סתומה. But of set, I don't know why I switched
to A and B here, but of set A, even though it's
unexplicated, you've got a חטאת and an עולה there. And of set
B, it's unexplicated and you have two עולות. olot Okay, so he
split them in half, one above and one below. So this one,
this set, you fulfilled your obligation, okay, because he got to designate
which was which. This set, the one that he did below, by
perforce was an עולה because they're both עולות. olot Okay? And therefore
the one that was below, you did not fulfill, excuse me, the
one that was, yeah, the one that was below, you did not
fulfill your obligation. Okay, so לא עשה כן, lo asah chen, he
didn't do this. אלא עשה שניים למעלה ושניים למטה. ela asah shnayim
l'ma'alah u'shnayim l'matah. ולא נמלך, v'lo nimlach, he didn't ask her. צריכה
שתביא עוד פרידה אחת ותקריבנה למעלה.
tzrichah she'tavi od pereidah achat
v'takrivena l'ma'alah. So
she has to go ahead and bring one other bird and bring
it above. Okay, because she's still obligated in an עולה. That's if
זה ממין אחד. zeh m'min echad. That's if they are all of
the same type of birds, either תור tor or בני יונה, b'nei
yonah, turtledove or pigeon. Okay, although I think a turtledove is a
type of pigeon, but whatever, anyway, because the other הלכה is, you
don't get, if you own a pair of something, you have to
pair it with the same type of bird. You don't get to
pair it with a different type of bird. Now, let's say it
is, however, מבית מינים, mibeit minim, okay, ומשני מינים. umishnei minim. Let's
say, however, ומשני מינים umishnei minim these are, you know, turtle doves,
and these are pigeons. Okay.
And now, but you know, she knows that they're they're whatever, but
you got confused, wait, which one was the turtle doves, which ones
were the pigeons, which ones did I do above, which ones did
I do below, like you don't know. Okay, so in that type
of a case, bottom line is, the עולה that you did above,
the one that needs the pair, the one that you didn't fulfill
your full obligation is the two עולות because you did one of
the עולות below. But what you don't remember effectively is, wait a
minute, you know, did I do the, how what would the question
be? If I did,
well, if you split them both, both had, oh, no, so both
of them at the end of the day, you have had two
עולות above, you know, two birds above, one was a תור tor
and one was a בן יונה. ben yonah. Okay, you had those
two above, right? And then below, you had a תור tor and
a בן יונה. ben yonah. So, so you should just say fine,
oh, but she doesn't remember, that's the point. She doesn't remember which
of these sets was which, which of these was the תור tor
and which was the בן יונה, ben yonah, okay, so she has
to bring the mate to the עולה. She owes an עולה mate
above, but she doesn't remember, wait, wait, wait, which one of this
was the set B and which one was the set A? If
this was the set B, right, then I need to mate this
with a בן יונה. ben yonah. I need an extra עולה. If
this was the set B, then I need an extra תור, tor,
I need an extra pigeon. To get it, so this set she
only satisfied half. But she doesn't remember if this set was the
turtle doves or the pigeons. So therefore she needs a turtle dove
and a pigeon because she needs to mate it with the other
half. Okay, משני מינים תביא שתים. mishnei minim tavi shtayim. So she
brings two. So we will, that's the easy part of the משנה.
mishnah. Okay, we're going to get to the more complicated part tomorrow,
but again at this stage the issue was that he split them,
they were not designated. So if he split them the simple point
is then you owe an עולה from this set. If they're all
the same pigeons, so you owe one pigeon. If some are pigeons
and some are turtle doves, then you don't know which set is
which and you have to mate it with the same thing, so
then you owe a turtle dove and a pigeon, a turtle dove,
a pigeon dove and what, a turtle dove and a pigeon, so
you owe one of each because either one might be the mate
that's required and that you bring as the עולה. Okay, the more
complicated case we will do tomorrow.
Alrighty.